Baris Kasikci

Assistant Professor Electrical Engineering and Computer Science University of Michigan

 $4820~\mathrm{BBB}$ 2260 Hayward Street Ann Arbor, MI 48109, USA +1 (734) 763-1560 barisk@umich.edu

http://web.eecs.umich.edu/~barisk

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research is centered around developing techniques, tools, and environments that help developers build more reliable, secure, and efficient software. I am interested in developing techniques and building systems that allow programmers to better reason about their code. I am also interested in system support for emerging hardware platforms, efficient runtime instrumentation, hardware and runtime support for enhancing system security, and program analysis.

EDUCATION

Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL)

Lausanne, Switzerland

Ph.D. in Computer Science

Sep. 2010–Dec. 2015

Thesis: Techniques for Detection, Root Cause Diagnosis,

and Classification of In-Production Concurrency Bugs

Advisor: Prof. George Candea

Middle East Technical University (METU)

Ankara, Turkey

Sep. 2002-Jun. 2006

M.Sc. in Electrical and Electronics Engineering

Sep. 2006-Jun. 2009

Thesis: Variability Modeling in Software Product Lines

Graduated with the top grade Advisor: Prof. Semih Bilgen

B.Sc. in Electrical and Electronics Engineering

Project: Embedded Target Estimation, Detection, and Tracking

Graduated with High Honors Advisor: Prof. Arzu Koc

AWARDS AND HONORS

Outstanding Reviewer Award, WWW	2017
Patrick Denantes Memorial Prize for outstanding PhD thesis, EPFL	2016
EuroSys Roger Needham Award for Best PhD. Thesis in Computer Systems in Europe	2016
Intel Corp. Software and Services Group, Grant	2014-2016
VMware Inc., Doctoral Fellowship	2014 – 2015
EPFL, Doctoral Fellowship	2010-2011
Scientific and Technological Research Council of Turkey, Master Scholarship	2006-2008
Middle East Technical University, Dean's High Honor List	2006
Middle East Technical University,	
Award for Best Team Performance, Undergraduate Final Project	2006
Turkish Customs Association, Scholarship	2002 - 2006

EMPLOYMENT

University of Michigan

Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA Sep. 2017-present

Assistant Professor

Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Department

Microsoft Research

 $Cambridge,\ United\ Kingdom$

Researcher

Aug. 2016-Aug. 2017

Research on computer systems and networks

Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL)

Lausanne, Switzerland

Postdoctoral Researcher

Dec. 2015–Jul. 2016

Research on software security

• I developed infrastructure that relies on hardware support to improve software security.

Research Assistant

Sep. 2010–Dec. 2015

Research on software reliability with an emphasis on concurrent software

- I developed **Gist**, the first technique for accurately, efficiently, and automatically diagnosing the root causes of in-production failures, by using a combination of static and dynamic program analysis.
- I developed **RaceMob**, the first automated in-production data race detection technique that can be kept always-on and provides high accuracy, by combining static data race detection with adaptive, crowdsourced dynamic data race detection.
- I developed **Portend**, a high-accuracy technique to classify data races according to their potential consequences under arbitrary memory models, by using symbolic program analysis to explore multiple program paths and schedules to determine the effects of data races.
- I developed **Bias-Free Sampling**, a technique that allows efficient sampling of rarely executed code (where bugs often lurk) without over-sampling frequently executed code, by using a new sampling algorithm and existing hardware support.

Intel Corp.

Santa Clara, CA, USA

Research Intern

Jul. 2015–Sep. 2015

Automated root cause diagnosis of failures and security enhancements using hardware support

• I developed a tool that allows developers to determine which program statements operate on a given data type at runtime using a mix of static program analysis and hardware support. In our experiments, this tool reduces the number of statements to examine during debugging by an order of magnitude. This tool is being extended internally at Intel.

• I began investigating hardware support for enhancing system security, in particular, efficient path profiling for auditing and detecting control flow hijack attacks.

VMware Inc. Palo Alto, CA, USA

Research and Development Intern

Jun. 2014–Sep. 2014

Automated debugging and runtime control flow tracking

- I implemented a runtime for efficient control flow tracking in software. This work formed the basis of my **Gist** work on root cause diagnosis.
- I designed and implemented an infrastructure to remotely debug and profile VMware VCenter virtual machine management software, while it is running in production. This infrastructure is used by VCenter developers at VMWare.

Microsoft Research Redmond, WA, USA

Research Intern Jun. 2013–Sep. 2013

Efficient runtime execution sampling technique and low overhead coverage measurement

- I worked on the design of the **Bias-Free Sampling** framework for efficient runtime sampling. I designed and implemented the bias-free sampling framework for managed code (i.e., C#). This tool is internally used at Microsoft.
- I designed and implemented a fault injection tool to detect resource leakage problems using dynamic binary instrumentation.

Siemens Corporate Technology

Istanbul, Turkey

Senior Software Engineer

Mar. 2008-May 2010

Embedded home and industrial automation software

• I designed and implemented a real-time embedded gateway software between Siemens communication processors and a building automation system using C++ on top of VxWorks.

Aselsan Electronic Industries

Ankara, Turkey

Software Engineer

May 2006–Mar. 2008

Embedded motor control and functional testing infrastructure

• I was responsible for a real-time embedded control software for turret motor control. I also designed and implemented a full-system functional testing software using C++ on top of VxWorks for Power PC architectures.

Student Intern

Jun. 2005-Jul. 2005

Embedded software development

• I developed embedded control software for a night vision camera using C++ and PIC assembly on a PIC microcontroller.

- [1] REPT: Reverse Debugging of Failures in Deployed Software. Xinyang Ge Weidong Cui, Baris Kasikci, Ben Niu, Upamanyu Sharma, Ruoyu Wang, and Insu Yun. *OSDI*, Carlsbad, USA, October 2018.
- [2] Foreshadow: Extracting the Keys to the Intel SGX Kingdom with Transient Out-of-Order Execution. Jo Van Bulck, Marina Minkin, Ofir Weisse, Daniel Genkin, Baris Kasikci, Frank Piessens, Mark Silberstein, Thomas F. Wenisch, Yuval Yarom, and Raoul Strackx. USENIX Security, Baltimore, USA, August 2018.
- [3] Cntr: Lightweight OS Containers. Jorg Thalheim, Pramod Bhatotia, Pedro Fonseca, and Baris Kasikci. *USENIX ATC*, Boston, USA, July 2018.
- [4] Lazy Diagnosis of In-Production Concurrency Bugs. Baris Kasikci, Weidong Cui, Xinyang Ge, and Ben Niu. Symp. on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP), Shanghai, China, October 2017.
- [5] Failure Sketching: A Technique for Automated Root Cause Diagnosis of In-Production Failures. Baris Kasikci, Benjamin Schubert, Cristiano Pereira, Gilles Pokam, and George Candea. Symp. on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP), Monterey, CA, October 2015.
- [6] Failure Sketches: A Better Way to Debug. Baris Kasikci, Benjamin Schubert, Cristiano Pereira, Gilles Pokam, Madanlal Musuvathi, and George Candea. Workshop on Hot Topics in Operating Systems (HotOS), Kartause Ittingen, Switzerland, May 2015.
- [7] Automated Classification of Data Races Under Both Strong and Weak Memory Models. Baris Kasikci, Cristian Zamfir, and George Candea. ACM Transactions on Programming Languages and Systems (TOPLAS), May 2015.
- [8] Efficient Tracing of Cold Code Via Bias-Free Sampling. Baris Kasikci, Thomas Ball, George Candea, John Erickson, and Madanlal Musuvathi. *USENIX ATC*, Philadelphia, PA, June 2014.
- [9] Lockout: Efficient Testing for Deadlock Bugs. Ali Kheradmand, Baris Kasikci, and George Candea.
 5th Workshop on Determinism and Correctness in Parallel Programming (WoDet), Salt Lake City, UT,
 March 2014.
- [10] RaceMob: Crowdsourced Data Race Detection. Baris Kasikci, Cristian Zamfir, and George Candea. Symp. on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP), Farmington, PA, November 2013.
- [11] Automated Debugging for Arbitrarily Long Executions. Cristian Zamfir, Baris Kasikci, Johannes Kinder, Edouard Bugnion, and George Candea. Workshop on Hot Topics in Operating Systems (HotOS), Santa Ana Pueblo, NM, May 2013.
- [12] CORD: A Collaborative Framework for Distributed Data Race Detection. Baris Kasikci, Cristian Zamfir, and George Candea. Workshop on Hot Topics in Dependable Systems (HotDep), Hollywood, CA, October 2012.
- [13] Data Races vs. Data Race Bugs: Telling the Difference with Portend. Baris Kasikci, Cristian Zamfir, and George Candea. Intl. Conf. on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS), London, UK, March 2012.
- [14] Scalable Modeling of Software Product Line Variability. Baris Kasikci and Semih Bilgen. Workshop on Scalable Modeling Techniques for Software Product Lines (SCALE), San Francisco, CA, August 2009.

Talks

• Greater Chicago Area Systems Research Workshop, University of Chicago (Invited Talk) May 2	018
Treated threat by stems research workshop, University of Chicago (hivited rank) way 25	010
• Purdue University (Invited Talk) May 2	2018
Hardware-Software Co-Design for Debugging and Performance Anlysis	
• Workshop on Resilient Systems, TU Dresden (Keynote) Apr. 2	2017
Symbolic Execution: A Gentle Introduction	
• Cyber In Bretagne Summer School (Invited Talk) Jul. 2	2016
Stamping Out Concurrency Bugs	
• Royal Holloway, University of London, Seminar Apr. 2	2016
• Georgia Institute of Technology, Seminar Apr. 2	2016
• Carnegie Mellon University, Seminar Apr. 2	2016
• University of Southern California, Seminar Mar. 2	2016
• University of Rochester, Seminar Mar. 2	2016
• Microsoft Research Redmond, Seminar Mar. 2	2016
• Microsoft Research Cambridge, Seminar Mar. 2	2016
• MPI Software Systems, Seminar Mar. 2	2016
• University College London, Seminar Mar. 2	2016
• Rice University, Seminar Feb. 2	2016
• University of Toronto, Seminar Feb. 2	2016
• University of Michigan, Seminar Feb. 2	2016
• Boston University, Seminar Feb. 2	2016
• Georgia Institute of Technology, Seminar Feb. 2	2016
• VMWare Research, Seminar Feb. 2	2016
• University of British Columbia, Seminar Feb. 2	2016
• Simon Fraser University, Seminar Jan. 2	2016
Automated Root Cause Diagnosis of In-Production Failures	
• Symposium on Operating System Principles (SOSP) Oct. 2	2015
• Intel Corp. Sep. 2	
• Google Sep. 2	
• VMware Inc. Sep. 2	
Failure Sketches: A Better Way to Debug	
• EcoCloud Annual Event Jun. 2	2015
• Hot Topics in Operating Systems (HotOS) May 2	2015
Efficient Tracing of Cold Code via Bias-Free Sampling	
• USENIX Annual Technical Conference (USENIX ATC) Jun. 2	2014
Lockout: Efficient Testing for Deadlock Bugs	
• Workshop on Determinism and Correctness in Parallel Programming (WoDet) Mar. 2	2014
RaceMob: Crowdsourced Data Race Detection. • Symposium on Operating System Principles (SOSP) Oct. 2	0∩19
 Symposium on Operating System Principles (SOSP) EPFL Systems Seminar Oct. 2 	
CoRD: A Collaborative Framework for Distributed Data Race Detection	.019

• Workshop on Hot Topics in System Dependability (HotDep) Data Races vs. Data Race Bugs: Telling the Difference with Portend	Oct. 2012
 International Conference on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS) 	Mar. 2012
How to Build Reliable Software?	Q 2011
• Seminar talk to the incoming undergraduate students at EPFL	Sep. 2011
Professional Service	
Journal Reviewer	
Transactions on Architecture and Code Optimization	2018
Transactions on Software Engineering	2015
Transactions on Software Engineering and Methodology	2015
PC Chair	
Workshop on System Software for Trusted Execution (co-located with CCS'18)	2018
Symposium on Cloud Computing Poster Session	2018
PC Member	
EuroSys	2019
Symposium on Cloud Computing International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems	2018 2017
World Wide Web Conference (WWW)	2017
International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis, Artifact Evaluation Committee	2014
Extended Review Committee	
Intl. Conf. on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems	2018
Shadow PC Member	2010
EuroSys Conference on Computer Systems (EuroSys)	2013, 2015
External Reviewer	2010, 2010
Symp. on Operating Systems Principles (SOSP)	2011. 2013
EuroSys Conf. on Computer Systems (EuroSys)	2011. 2013
USENIX Annual Technical Conf. (USENIX ATC)	2011, 2012
Intl. Conf. on Compiler Construction (CC)	2017
Workshop on Hot Topics in Operating Systems (HotOS)	2011, 2013
Conf. on Innovative Data Systems Research (CIDR)	2013
Intl. Conf. on Dependable Systems and Networks (DSN)	2011, 2013
Symposium on Cloud Computing (SOCC) Intl. SPIN Workshop on Model Checking of Software (SPIN)	2012 2011
Committee Member	
EPFL Doctoral School of Computer and Communication Sciences Audit Committee	2015
24 F1 Doctoral School of Computer and Communication Sciences Audit Committee	2019
Teaching	

Introduction to Operating Systems (EECS 482) (undergrad level, University of Michigan) 2018, 2019 Advanced Topics in Operating Systems (EECS 582) (grad level, University of Michigan) 2017, 2019

RESEARCH MENTORING

Ofir Weisse (Ph.D.)

Sep. 2017-present

• Ofir and I are working on making system security more useful and usable. We primarily focus on techniques to effectively and efficiently migrate legacy code into cloud environments, while improving security properties using a combination of system support and new hardware technologies.

Lisa Zhou (1st year Master's)

Sep. 2015-Feb. 2016

• Lisa and I worked on using hardware support for improving the security of software systems. In that regard, Lisa and Benjamin (see below) built a framework for reproducing security bugs in large applications (e.g., Chrome).

Benjamin Schubert (3rd year undergraduate)

Feb. 2015-Dec. 2015

• Benjamin and I worked on a framework that enables reliably reproducing failures in systems software like Apache and MySQL. We used this framework to evaluate my **Gist** work on root cause diagnosis. We extended this framework to encompass security vulnerabilities.

Ali Kheradmand (3rd year undergraduate)

Jul. 2013-Sep.2013

Ali and I worked on the **Lockout** project and developed a technique to systematically perturb program
executions (without modifying program semantics) to increase the probability of deadlock manifestation. Ali is currently pursuing his Ph.D. at UIUC.

Radu Coman (Master's thesis)

Jan. 2012–Sep. 2012

• Radu and I surveyed common concurrency bug patterns in open source software. After we identified data races as a common bug pattern among the 100 bugs we looked at in Google Code, we built a static data race detector, which I used in my **RaceMob** project. Radu is currently a senior software engineer at Ixia.

FUNDING

Michigan Cambridge Research Initiative, 15K USD, PI 2018

Applications Driving Architectures, 1,245M USD, PI 2018

Intel SSG, Automated Performance Optimization, 75K USD, PI 2018

LANGUAGES

English: fluent French: fluent Turkish: native German: beginner

References

Available upon request